[Music]
Reedman
reads the Giver by Lois Lowry narrated by Fraser Reedman chapter
6 "Lily, please hold still," Mother said again. Lily, standing in front of her, fidgeted
impatiently. "I can tie them myself," she complained. "I always
have." "I know that," Mother replied, straightening the hair ribbons on the
little girl's braids. "But I also know that they constantly come loose and more
often than not, they're dangling down your back by afternoon. Today, at least, we
want them to be neatly tied and to stay neatly tied." "I don't like hair ribbons. I'm glad
I only have to wear them one more year," Lily said irritably. "Next year I get my
bicycle, too," she added more cheerfully. "There are good things each year," Jonas reminded
her. "This year you get to start your volunteer hours remember last year, when
you became a Seven, you were so happy to get your front button
jacket?" The little girl nodded and looked down at herself, at the jacket with its
row of large buttons that designated her as a Seven. Fours, Fives, and Sixes all
wore jackets that fastened down the back so that they would have to help each
other dress and would learn interdependence. The front button jacket was the first sign of
independence, the first very visible symbol of growing up. The bicycle, at 9 would be the
powerful emblem of moving gradually out into the community, away from the
protective family unit. Lily grinned and wriggled away from her mother. "And this
year you get your Assignment," she said to Jonas in an excited voice. "I hope you get
Pilot. And that you take me flying!" "Sure I will," said Jonas. "And I'll
get a special little Paro that just fits you, and I'll take you up to uh maybe
20,000 ft and open the door, and—" Jonas, Mother warned. "I was only joking," Jonas
groaned. "I don't want Pilot, anyway. If I get Pilot I'll put it in a peel Come on,"
Mother said. She gave Lily's ribbons a final tug. "Jonas? Are you ready? Did you
take your pill a what to get a good seat in the
Auditorium." She prodded Lily to the front door and Jonas followed there was a short ride to the
Auditorium, Lily waving to her friends from her seat on the back of Mother's
bicycle. Jonas stowed his bicycle beside mothers and made his way through the throng to find his
group. The entire community attended the Ceremony each year. For the parents, it
meant 2 days holiday from work; they sat together in the huge hall. Children sat
with their parents until they went, one by one, to the stage. Father, though, would not join
Mother in the audience right away. For the earliest ceremony, the Naming, the
Nurturers brought the new children to the stage. Jonas, from his place in the
balcony with the 11s searched the Auditorium for a glimpse of
Father. It wasn't at all hard to spot the nurturer section at the
front; coming from it were the whales and howls of the new children who sat
squirming on the nurturer laps. At every other public ceremony, the audience was
silent and attentive. But once a year, they all smiled indulgently at the
commotion from the little ones waiting to receive their names and families.
Jonas finally caught his father's eye and waved. Father grinned and waved back,
then held up the hand of the new child on his lap, making it wave,
too. It wasn't Gabriel. Gabe was back at the Nurturing Center today, being cared
for by the night crew. He had been given an un usual and special reprieve from
the committee, and granted an additional year of nurturing before his Naming and
Placement. Father had gone before the committee with a plea on behalf of
Gabriel, who had not yet gained the weight appropriate to his days of life
nor begun to sleep soundly enough at night to be placed with his family unit.
Normally such a new child would be labeled Inadequate and released from the
community. Instead, as a result of Father's plea, Gabriel had been labeled
Uncertain and given the additional year.
He would continue to be nurtured at the Center and would spend his nights with
Jonas's family unit. Each family member, including Lily, had been required to sign
a pledge that they would not become attached to this little temporary guest
that they would relinquish him without protest or appeal when he was assigned
to his own family unit at next year's Ceremony. At least, Jonas thought, after
Gabriel was placed next year, they would still see him often because he would be
part of the community. If he were released, they would not see him again.
Ever. Those who were released— —even as new children were sent Elsewhere and never
returned to the community. Father had not had to release
a single new child this year, so Gabriel would have represented a real failure in
sadness. Even Jonas, though he didn't hover over the little one the way Lily
and his father did, was glad that Gabe had not been
released. The first Ceremony began right on time, and Jonas watched as one after
another each new child was given a name and handed by the Nurturers to its new family
unit. For some, it was a first child. But many came to the stage accompanied by
another child beaming with pride to receive a little brother or sister, the
way Jonas had when he was about to be a Five. Asher poked Jonas's arm. "Remember
when we got Philippa he asked in a loud whisper. Jonas nodded. It had only been
last year. Asher's parents had waited quite a long time before applying for a
second child. Maybe Jonah suspected, they had been so exhausted by Asher's lively
foolishness that they had needed a little time. Two of their group, Fiona and
another female named Thea, were missing temporarily, waiting with their parents
to receive new children But it was rare that there was such an age gap between
children and a family unit. When her family ceremony was completed, Fiona took the seat that had
been saved for her in the row ahead of Asher and Jonas. She turned and whispered
to them, "He's cute. But I don't like his name very much." She made a face and
giggled. Fiona's new brother had been named Bruno. It wasn't a great name, Jonas
thought, like— —well, like Gabriel, for example. But it was
okay. The audience applause, which was enthusiastic at each Naming, rose in an
exuberant swell when one parental pair, glowing with pride, took a male new child
and heard him named Caleb.
This new Caleb was a replacement child.
The couple had lost their first Caleb, a cheerful little
Four. Loss of a child was very, very rare.
The community was extraordinarily safe, each citizen watchful and protective of all
children. But somehow the first little Caleb had wandered away unnoticed, and
had fallen into the river. The entire community had performed the Ceremony of Loss together,
murmuring the name Caleb throughout an entire day, less and less frequently,
softer in volume, as the long and somber day went on, so that the little Force
seemed to fade away gradually from everyone's consciousness. Now, at this special Naming,
the community performed the brief murmur of replacement Ceremony, repeating the
name for the first time since the loss: softly and slowly at first, then faster
and with greater volume, as the couple stood on the stage with a new child
sleeping in the mother's arms. It was as if the first Caleb were
returning. Another new child was given the name Roberto, and Jonas remembered
that Roberto the Old had been released only last week. But there was no murmur
of replacement Ceremony for the new little Roberto. Release was not the same as
Loss. He sat politely through the ceremonies of Two and Three and Four,
increasingly bored as he was each year.
Then a break for midday meal— —served outdoors— —and back again to the seats, for
the Fives, Sixes, Sevens, and finally, last of the first day ceremonies, the Eights.
Jonas watched and cheered as Lily marched proudly to the stage, became an
Eight and received the identifying jacket that she would wear this year,
this one with smaller buttons and, for the first time, pockets, indicating that
she was mature enough now to keep track of her own small belongings. She he stood solemnly
listening to the speech of firm instructions on the responsibilities of
Eight and doing volunteer hours for the first time. But Jonas could see that Lily,
though she seemed attentive, was looking longingly at the row of gleaming
bicycles, which would be presented tomorrow morning to the Nines. Next year Lily Billy Jonas
thought. It was an exhausting day, and even Gabriel, retrieved in his basket
from the Nurturing Center, slept soundly that night.
Finally it was the morning of the Ceremony of 12 Now Father sat beside Mother in the
audience. Jonas could see them applauding dutifully as the Nines, one by one wield
their new bicycles, each with its gleaming name tag attached to the back, from the
stage. He knew that his parents cringed a little, as he did, when Fritz, who lived in
the dwelling next door to theirs, received his bike and almost immediately
bumped into the podium with it. Fritz was a very award awward child
who' been summoned for chastisement again and again. His transgressions were
small ones, always: shoes on the wrong feet, schoolwork misplaced, failure to
study adequately for a quiz. But each such error reflected
negatively on his parents' guidance and infringed on the community's sense of order and
success. Jonas and his family had not been looking forward to Fritz's bicycle,
which they realized would probably too often be dropped on the front walk
instead of wheeled neatly into its port.
Finally the Nines were all resettled in their seats, each having wheeled a
bicycle outside where it would be waiting for its owner at the end of the
day. Everyone always chuckled and made small jokes when the Nines rode home for
the first time well me to show you how to ride?" older friends would call. "I know
you've never been on a bike before!" But invariably the grinning Nines, who in
technical violation of the rule had been practicing secretly for weeks, would
mount and ride off in perfect bance training wheels never touching the
ground. Then the Tens. Jonas never found the Ceremony of 10 particularly
interesting— —only timec consuming as each child's hair was snipped neatly into its
distinguishing cut: females lost their braids at 10 and males, too, relinquished
their long childish hair and took on the more manly short style which exposed
their ears. Laborers moved quickly to the stage with brooms and swept away the
mounds of discarded hair. Jonas could see the parents of the new T stir and murmur,
and he knew that this evening, in many dwellings, they would be snipping and
straightening the hastily done haircuts, trimming them into a neater line
Els It seemed a short time ago that Jonas had undergone the Ceremony of 11
be remembered that it was not one of the more interesting
ones. By 11 one was only waiting to be 12
It was simply a marking of time with no meaningful changes. There was new clothing: different
undergarments for the females, whose bodies were beginning to change longer
trousers for the males, with a specially shaped pocket for the small calculator
that they would use this year in school those were simply presented in
wrapped packages without an accompanying speech. Break for midday
meal jonice realized he was hungry. He and his groupmates congregated by the
tables in front of the Auditorium and took their packaged food. Yesterday there
had been merryment at lunch, a lot of teasing in energy. But today the group
stood anxiously, separate from the other children. Jonas watched the new Nines
gravitate toward their waiting bicycles, each one admiring his or her name tag He
saw the Tens stroking their new shortened hair, the females shaking their
heads to feel the unaccustomed lightness without the heavy braids they had worn
for so long. "I heard about a guy who was absolutely certain he was going to be
assigned Engineer," Asher muttered as they ate, "and instead they gave him Sanitation
Laborer. He went out the next day, jumped into the river, swam across, and joined
the next community he came to. Nobody ever saw him again." Jonas laughed. "Somebody made that
story up, Ash," he said. "My father said he heard that story when he was a
12 But Asher wasn't reassured. He was eyeing the river where it was visible
behind the Auditorium. "I can't even swim very well," he said. "My swimming instructor
said that I don't have the right boyishness or something."
"Buoyancy," Jonas corrected him. "Whatever. I don't have it. I sink." "Anyway," Jonas
pointed out, "have you ever once known of anyone— —I mean really known for sure,
Asher, not just heard about it— —who joined another
community?" "No," Asher admitted reluctantly.
"But you can. It says so in the rules. If you don't fit in, you can apply for
Elsewhere and be released. My mother says that once, about 10 years ago, someone
applied and was gone the next day and he chuckled. "She told me that because
I was driving her crazy. She Threatened to apply for Elsewhere." "She was
joking." "I know. But it was true, what she said, that someone did that once. She said
that it was really true. Here today and gone tomorrow. Never seen again. Not even a Ceremony of
Release." Jonas shrugged. It didn't worry him. How could someone not fit in? The
community was so meticulously ordered, the choices so carefully made. Even the
Matching of Spouses was given such weighty consideration that sometimes an
adult who applied to receive a spouse waited months or even years before a
Match was approved and announced. All of the factors— —disposition,
energy level, intelligence, and interests— —had to correspond and to interact
perfectly. Jonas's mother, for example, had higher intelligence than his father; but
his father had a calmer disposition. They balanced each other. Their Match, which like ball
Matches had been monitored by the Committee of Elders for 3 years before
they could apply for children, had always been a successful
one. Like the Matching of Spouses and the Naming and Placement of new children the
Assignments were scrupulously thought through by the Committee of
Elders. He was certain that his Assignment, whatever it was to be, and
ashers too, would be the right one for them. He only wished that the midday
break would conclude, that the audience would re-enter the Auditorium, and the suspense would
end. As if in answer to his unspoken wish, the signal came and the crowd began to
move toward the doors
[Music]